# Javed Shahbaz

## **FULL STACK WEB DEVELOPER**

javedshahbaz007@gmail.com| GitHub | LinkedIn | Twitter | Portfolio

#### **SUMMARY**

Full Stack Software Developer and Artificial Intelligence Developer with a Computer Science background and 1+ years of Freelance Experience. Specialized in ReactJS, Ruby on Rails with PostgreSQL, and Python. Strengths include pair-programming, collaboration, and communication. Eager to engage with innovative ideas in a growth environment, utilizing the latest technologies to further enhance skills and expertise while collaborating with fellow developers.

### **SKILLS**

Front-End: JavaScript, React JS, Redux, HTML5, CSS3 Back-End: Ruby, Ruby on Rails, MySQL, PostgreSQL

Tools & Methods: Git, GitHub, Chrome Developer Tools, Responsive Development, Test Driven Development

Professional: Remote Pair-Programming, Teamwork, Collaboration with diverse teams

#### **EXPERIENCE**

HIGHLIGHTED PERSONAL PROJECTS

Remote

## Full Stack Web Development Student & Mentor

February 2023 – Present

Mastered intermediate and advanced topics in full-stack development (including Rails, Git, and DS&A challenges) while building 10+ full-stack projects both independently and via pair-programming. Some of them are listed below:

**Movie Website** — The JavaScript capstone project is about building our own web application based on two external APIs.

Built with: JavaScript, HTML5 & CSS3 | GH repo

**Book Website** — A digital library platform designed for avid readers to manage their book collection seamlessly. Users can easily add, delete, and list books with intuitive interactive elements. The design emulates the comforting ambiance of a traditional library, featuring responsive bookshelf visuals.

• Built with: JavaScript ES6, HTML5 & CSS3 | GH repo

MICROVERSE Remote

Mentor (Volunteer)

March 2023 – Present

- Mentored 5 junior web developers, providing detailed technical support through over 20 code reviews.
- Proposed innovative improvements to code organization, resulting in a 30% improvement in code quality and a 20% improvement in overall performance.
- Implemented strategies to help maintain motivation and promote longevity in the program, resulting in a 35% increase in program retention.

#### **EDUCATION**

**MICROVERSE** 

February 2023 - December 2023

#### Remote Full Stack Web Development Program, Full Time

 Spent 1300+ hours mastering algorithms, data structures, and full-stack development while simultaneously developing projects with Ruby, Rails, JavaScript, React, and Redux. • Developed skills in remote pair-programming using GitHub, industry-standard gitflow, and daily standups to communicate and collaborate with international remote developers.

PIAIC
Remote Artificial Intelligence Program, Full Time

January 2022 – January 2023

- Acquired proficiency in Python, focusing on data analysis techniques and applications.
- Delved deep into the principles and practical applications of both Machine Learning and Deep Learning, enhancing predictive modeling and algorithmic skills.

NCBA & E, Lahore.

## MS in Computer Science, Software Engineering

February 2014 – February 2016

- Mastered Advanced Algorithms Analysis and Design, emphasizing efficient problem-solving techniques.
- Delved into Software Quality Assurance, applying best practices to ensure software reliability and robustness.